Guide to the Richard Kressler and Laylen Sweet Collection of American Art Posters 1891-1899, 1919 PR 334
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Richard Kressler and Laylen Sweet collection of American art posters
1891-1899, 1919
PR 334
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
3.0 Linear feet in one oversize folder
The collection includes 23 art posters, dating principally from 1891-1899, representing covers of publications including Harper's, Lippincott's, Scribner's, and The Century magazine.
Kressler, Richard N.
Sweet, Laylen H.
Immediate Source of Acquisition Note
Gift of Susan Phillips and Thomas Kenny in memory of Richard Kressler and Laylen Sweet, July 2017.
Scope and Contents note
The collection includes 23 art posters. All but one are of covers of publications from 1891-1899, including Harper's, Lippincott's, Scribner's, and The Century magazine. The lone exception is a reproduction of an 1848 lithograph of Broadway, published by Valentine's Manual in 1919. Most of the posters are signed by the artist, especially Edward Penfield for Harper's. The container list includes a detailed inventory.
Arrangement Note
The container list below is arranged first by title and then chronologically. The posters themselves are all encapsulated, with most enclosures holding more than one poster, though not in the order of the container list.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers by appointment only.
Related Archival Materials Note
New-York Historical Society also holds an extensive collection of art posters compiled over time; see the Art Poster File (PR 55-1).
Biographical/Historical Note
Richard N. Kressler (1930-2016) was, for most of his career, an advertising manager for New York’s Magee Carpet Company and, later, marketing manager for Revlon, Inc. In the 1970s, Kressler, along with his brother Dan and friend Laylen H. (Lee) Sweet (1926-2012), bought a classic Brooklyn brownstone, at 233 Baltic Street, which led to his long involvement with the Heights and Hill Community Council and the Brooklyn Historical Society. Kressler and Sweet collected art and antiques, with works on paper of particular interest to the two, especially given Sweet’s professional background as a graphic designer. The works donated to N-YHS were part of a collection that had been displayed in the dining room of their Cobble Hill home.
(Source: From Richard Kressler's obituary in the on-line Brooklyn Daily and information provided by the donor.)
Gould, J. J., Jr., 1880-1935, (Joseph J.) -- Pictorial works; Penfield, Edward, 1866-1925 -- Pictorial works; Book & magazine posters -- 19th century; Century magazine; Harper's magazine; Lippincott's magazine; Scribner's magazine
- Harper’s., 1893 May (Folder 1, Enclosure 3)
  Scope and Contents Note
  Artwork: May Day girl, not signed.
- Harper’s., 1894 July (Folder 1, Enclosure 4)
  Artwork: Woman with firecrackers, signed Edward Penfield.
- Harper’s., 1894 October (Folder 1, Enclosure 2)
  Artwork: Man with pipe bicycling, signed by Edward Penfield.
- Harper’s., 1894 November (Folder 1, Enclosure 4)
  Artwork: Man/woman, Yale/Harvard; signed Edward Penfield.
- Harper’s., 1895 August (Folder 1, Enclosure 2)
  Artwork: Woman reaching for magazine from end of rope, not signed.
- Harper’s., 1896 June (Folder 1, Enclosure 3)
  Artwork: Woman reading in rocking chair, signed by Edward Penfield.
- Harper’s. "Tom Sawyer, Detective", 1896 August (Folder 1, Enclosure 1)
  Artwork: male in swimsuit with cigarette/woman in full dress outfit, signed by Edward Penfield and with symbol.
- Harper’s., 1896 September (Folder 1, Enclosure 1)
  Artwork: Woman holding book, signed with symbol (Edward Penfield?)
- Harper’s., 1896 November (Folder 1, Enclosure 2)
  Artwork: passenger carriage, horse, driver; signed by Edward Penfield in two places, and with symbol.
- Harper’s., 1897 March (Folder 1, Enclosure 2)
  Artwork: winter promenade, signed by Edward Penfield.
- Harper’s. Christmas, 1897 (Folder 1, Enclosure 3)
  Artwork: Man reading on high-backed bench, signed by Edward Penfield.
- Harper’s., 1898 May (Folder 1, Enclosure 4)
  Artwork: Roosters, signed wth symbol (Edward Penfield?).
- Harper’s., 1899 January (Folder 1, Enclosure 3)
  Artwork: Horse-drawn sleigh, not signed.
- Harper’s., 1899 March (Folder 1, Enclosure 4)
  Artwork: farmer, horse, plow; not signed.
- Lippincott’s. "'A Tame Surrender, A History of the Chicago Strike,' by Capt. Chas. King, U.S.A.", 1895 March (Folder 1, Enclosure 7)
  Artwork by Will Caroueville.
- Lippincott’s. "'Flotsam' by Owen Hall"; "'The Washingtons in Virginia' by Anne H. Wharton", 1896 April (Folder 1, Enclosure 7)
  Artwork by J.J. Gould, Jr.
- Lippincott’s. "'Jason Hildreth's Identity' by Virna Wood", 1897 May (Folder 1, Enclosure 7)
  Artwork by J.J. Gould.
- Scribner's. "R.H. Davis's War Articles; Mahan's Paul Jones; Manila Etc.", 1891 July (Folder 1, Enclosure 8)
- Scribner's. "'The Chinese Must Go': Andrews' History", 1895 October (Folder 1, Enclosure 8)
  Artwork by George M. Reeves.
- The Olympian Games Depicted by Correspondent and Artist of Scribner's, 1896 (Folder 1, Enclosure 8)
- The Century. "A New Life of Napoleon", 1894 (Folder 1, Enclosure 5)
  Designed by E. Grasset.
- The Century. "Napoleon in Egypt", 1895 June (Folder 1, Enclosure 6)
  Designed and artwork by E. Grasset.
- "Broadway, Both Sides, From Battery Place to Tin Pot Alley, (Now Exchange Alley,) in 1848", Circa 1919 (Folder 1, Enclosure 6)
  Reproduction of an 1848 lithograph by Jones & Newman, published for Valentine's Manual Vol. III, 1919.